So, this is Boris Journey, and he's the
creator of our friend Claude Code, and
these guys have just released their AI
native SDLC playbook. So, if this is a
new concept to you, SDLC is the software
development life cycle. Typically, in a
human workflow, it looks something like
this. You plan, you design, you build
it, you test it, you deploy it, and put
it into production, depending on what
type of an app it is, and then you need
to look at maintenance. And then you go
right back to the start for the next
feature, bug, or release. So, this new
document from Anthropic is all about how
the team there, including Boris, work in
terms of their new AI native software
development life cycle. So, let's give
it a rapid breakdown. So, the big idea
here is code is no longer the
bottleneck, it's your process. So,
before agents came along, this is pretty
much how an SDLC looked. We had the
planning stage, design, build, test,
deploy, and maintain. The part that took
the longest and was typically the most
expensive was the build stage. But, that
all changed with agents. This part here
has been squashed down to this part
here. Look at all this time here we've
reclaimed. So, essentially, what
Anthropic are saying we've done great to
shrink this, we're two times faster, but
how do we improve all these other steps
with agents as well? So, traditionally,
in our planning stage, we would sit
down, gather requirements, create PRDs,
have workshops, talk to stakeholders,
pulling it all together. In this new
world, we start by getting the agents to
interview us about the feature, the bug,
or the product that we're building in
order to build up context. I use my own
discovery skill called switch dimension
discovery, you could use Realm me from
Matt Pocock, or you could use something
like requirements discovery from Cursor.
So, what you want to do is make sure the
agent asks you repeated questions until
it has a complete understanding of the
feature you're building or the bug
you're trying to solve. You're dumping
as much of your experience, domain
experience, and context into this
conversation. So, the agent synthesizes
pain points straight from the sources,
and then captures them in this intent.md
file, which is human-readable and
machine-actionable.
So, Anthropic is formalizing this idea
around an intent.md file. So, in the
traditional SDLC, the idea passed to a
backlog of user entries, user stories,
story points, ownership transfers,
handoff. What we're talking about in the
AI-native world is the originator of the
issue, the feature, the product,
whatever, brainstorms with Claude and
writes the result down as the intent.md.
So, for each one of these steps as we
move through, we're going to be
developing what's called an artifact
chain. First, we start with an intent.md
file, then we're going to have a spec,
etc., as we go through the steps. That's
building the artifact chain. So, in your
project using Cursor, Claude, Code,
Codex, whatever you want, you're just
creating a folder called intent, and
within that, that's where you're going
to save your intent.md file. So, in my
planning stage here, I might have a chat
with my agent about adding dark mode as
a feature, and I talk about what I want,
how I want it to operate, and then we go
and create an intent.md file from that.
Then, I get the agent to save that as
the intent.md file in the intent folder
as proposed by Anthropic. And of course,
with any of these artifacts, your team
can do whatever they want in terms of a
workflow. I think what's important here
is that you start to standardize it and
not chop and change it too often. That
way, the team, the agents, the skills,
all work on the same workflow, and you
can grow from there. Now, once that
intent.md file is created, it doesn't
stop there. It's It's suggested that the
originator of the intent goes back over
what the agent has written to correct
anything and make sure that both of them
are happy. Now, the person that creates
this intent.md file is called the
originator, and that doesn't have to be
a specialist on the team. That can be
anybody who wants to create the intent.
It could be a customer who's putting in
a bug request. It could be a product
manager who has an idea for a feature.
It could be a developer who wants to
capture a process improvement. So, you
might have your own intent capture skill
that produces something similar to this.
What you might do over time as you're
collecting more forms of intent, you
might prefix the name of the intent
before your intent.md file. This is
something I've been doing myself and
teach on my course. I call it discovery,
not intent, but again, it's the same
idea. So, the intent really can be
captured by anyone. Could be a
developer, uh a customer submitting a
bug. They're basically just dropping
their thoughts into this intent.md file.
But then it is the product owner that
should review these in the form of a
backlog. These could simply be ordered
files in a markdown file. All these
ideas could be captured in Notion or
Linear and then organized by either a
product owner or in some cases I'll
actually use my agents to triage the
backlog of issues. You can see they can
assign tags like front-end, smaller
large tasks, whether it's a feature, and
even the priority level. So then we're
moving from the intent artifact to the
spec artifact. Anthropic is suggesting
that once the intent is committed or
signed off in some way that you create a
hook or a process that the spec is
automatically generate. So, Anthropic
gives us a sample prompt we might use to
take our intent and turn it into a spec.
They're not giving us specific skills
here, but we could certainly create a
skill around this. So, essentially, read
the attached intent.md and produce a
requirements and design spec. Apply
skills available to you to plan and
conform to brand guidelines and then
document the spec fully in spec.md.
Depending on your workflow, your
organization, you could just use the
vanilla plan mode within Cursor or
Claude Code or Codex or you could just
go and create a skill that creates
bespoke specs specific to how your team
likes to work. There really isn't a
one-size-fits-all here.
Now, when that spec is created, it could
just be through a vanilla agent or you
might also have a set of guidelines or
policies or even skills that make sure
that style guides are applied and
however the spec is generated is based
on the best practices of your
organization. This might be in an
agents.md file. It could be encoded into
a set of skills. You want to make sure
that those skills and policies are
adhered to in your governance
considerations for when the spec is
being generated. And that applies to all
of the artifacts in this chain. A quick
diversion to talk about our sponsor,
Neon. If you're using agents heavily in
your SDLC, I highly recommend you check
them out. I've been using Neon for years
for all my database needs. I've talked
loads about how Neon is ideal for agent
workflows with their awesome branching
feature. What I love about Neon is
they're totally agent first. So, in all
my agents, here's an example of Cursor.
I've got their MCP and the CLI and their
set of skills plugged in. So, I never
even have to touch the dashboard. The
agent knows what to do with all their
services. If you haven't checked in on
Neon lately, it's now a full-fledged
platform. It has managed better auth
included, which links to your database.
You've also got long-running functions
with no timeouts, S3 compatible object
storage for all your files in your
projects. If you're building projects
and working with agents, I highly
recommend Neon for an easy life. Channel
subscribers can check them out via the
link in the description down below. So,
let's get back to the SDLC. So, next up,
we're moving into build mode. So, it
starts essentially by the engineer
involved in the process pulling in the
intent and the spec and feeding it into
Cloud Code either in or in Cursor in
plan mode or something like that.
Basically, feeding the intent and the
spec. So, what we get then is a plan.md
file. So, what Anthropic are suggesting
is you interrogate the plan by asking
what changes could break. Essentially,
you want to get to a point where if you
were just to hand over this plan.md file
to an engineer, they could go and
implement the changes without reference
to the intent or spec documents. Now,
that's actually an important point
because we're not going to have one
agent carry out all of these different
stages in the software development life
cycle. We're going to have a context
window. We're going to have a thread of
conversations. Independent agents,
sub-agents are going to handle this
process. So, in that world, and here's
just an example from one of my own
workflows, you've got multiple different
agents working on the problem. You want
to hand off your planning, your intent
as documents to each one, so it can
start from scratch without an
understanding of the previous
conversation that happened.
So, when the engineer is happy, they go
and proceed with the plan. You've
probably seen 50 ways to write a plan,
but essentially what Anthropic are
saying is you break it down into the
files that need to be changed, the order
of work or type of to-do list, any kind
of risks, constraints, and then proof.
So, you want some kind of success
criteria and checks inevitably to make
sure that the work was done correctly.
This could come in a deterministic form
of linting and tests. A big part of the
process in an enterprise company is
going to be governance. So, what
Anthropic suggests is that you're saving
versions of your plan, your intent, your
spec.md, who touches them, and how they
are evolved. Companies I've worked with
find this part particularly hard, but
it's But, it's really important if you
want to track the leading and lag
indicators for your projects and really
prove out your Dora metrics or see how
effective AI actually is becoming in
your workflows. So, in terms of making
your build mode fast, Anthropic suggests
you use auto mode. It really does depend
though on your own organization. What I
suggest is that when you've got a
locked-down environment that you're
working in, that you actually start to
work in the repository with a set of
dialed-in permissions, and that you're
ex- secting them as you go. Once you've
built up a policy of what's fair use,
what tools the agents can access, what
web sources, what packages they're
pulling, and you lock that down in terms
of cursor or cloud permissions, you're
going to be able to have your agents
move a lot faster without you involved.
There are a lot of elements in making
sure auto mode runs smoothly and you've
got a tight blast radius for your agent.
Not for the context of this video, but
hopefully I'll cover more on that again.
The team also suggests work trees, so
you can have multiple agents work on
multiple things at the same time. If
that's completely over your head, I've
got a full video on my channel covering
Git and Git worktrees if you're just
getting used to them when it comes to
working with agents. So, a big part of
keeping this process autonomous, keeping
things updated, and keeping things on
rail are the usage of hooks.
So, as an example, in the build phase,
we might update the plan once the
implementation is complete. We might
block the agent from working on certain
folders or prevent it from operating an
NPM package that we haven't signed off
on yet. Linting has been around for a
long time. It's essentially a
deterministic or a coded way of running
through our code or our documents and
checking that certain criteria are there
or not there. Or that we're matching a
particular syntax. It's going to run
through the files, the tests will pass
or not. It's going to be a binary yes or
no. Something you'll get in a good agent
harness is the ability to run subagents.
So, once the plan is in place, this is
actually baked into Cursor Cloud Code
Codex. It divides the plan into various
different tasks that can be done
independently. And if some are in
parallel, it can use worktrees. So, we
end up having multiple agents and
subagents working on the build step. So,
after we're finished building, we move
into the test phase. In the traditional
software development life cycle, this
can be a step that really holds things
up. I might have finished a piece of
work, pushed it into development, and
then I have to wait a couple of days for
a tester to come along or a QA. Then
there's some changes, feedback, etc. The
whole cycle takes quite a lot of time.
In the AI software development life
cycle, we want the agent to do as much
testing as possible before a human
engineer or QA gets near it. Now, sorry
if this diagram diverges a little bit
from Anthropic we're talking about, but
this is the workflow I've been teaching
on my course at Switch Dimension, which
is really similar. So, essentially, once
we finish the build step here, we move
into testing, linting, end-to-end
review. The agent write tests to make
sure nothing is breaking when developed
and make sure those tests pass.
It's going to lint and build the project
to make sure there's no errors. And if
you're advanced enough and you're using
something like Playwright, Test-Driven
Development, Cursor Browser, you can
actually get the agent to test the
software and take screenshots. This is
actually something that Cursor Cloud
agents do really well. They'll actually
spin up a server and test the software
for you and give you a screen recording.
So, theoretically, once the testing is
complete and it's fairly rigorous, it's
going to save you a whole lot of time
when it comes to the human review stage.
Anthropic also suggests that you apply
evals to any skill change or any model
upgrade. Now, this really is optimizing,
but the idea is that you have continuous
evaluations in your continuous
integration. So, basically, you might
collect collect 20 or so issues or
things that you might have solved in the
code base. You have a set of expected
outcomes for those, and whenever you
have a new model, a new scale, or a new
fundamental change to how you do your
work, you can run this to see if your
software development life cycle
regresses or not. So, now we're getting
to the deploy stage. Essentially, we've
done our human review. We're going to
get the agent to merge or we're going to
get it to create a pull request to the
main repository based on whatever
changes it made. So, essentially, we
have a development branch, we have a
production branch, and our agent is
after making some changes on its own
branch or in a work tree. So, it's made
something called a pull request where
it's saying, "Hey, I made some changes.
I want you to take a look at them, and
if you're happy, you can go and add them
into the main code base." So, Anthropic
is suggesting as part of your continuous
integration or whenever a pull request
is made that you get Claude to jump in
and review it against your policies and
your security protocols. And all this is
done asynchronously. Now, the agent
might have its own comments on this PR
saying it doesn't accept it or it wants
some changes made in and and in
Anthropic's SDLC, you've got a separate
instance of Claude code reviewing those
comments. And of course, it might have
different policies based on what
agents.md, what skills.md, what hooks,
what linting it has in place. In terms
of governance, you might even have a
hook in place here that would block
deployment unless a specific permission
has been granted, unless a specific
person approves, or a release gate is
met. Here's an example of a set of
permissions that might be used as part
of that stage. So, once the pull request
is complete, you have another agent that
runs the security, the CI preview. This
could be deterministic with some form of
linting and gate checking, as well as
just having an agent like cursor, bug
bot, or Claude security review come in
and check for any errors. And that
finally brings us to the maintenance
step. So, I think this is where the
workflow gets really aspirational. So,
we look at our whole workflow here.
We've moved to planning, design,
building, testing, deploying, and now
we've reached maintenance. So, at this
point, either our issue is fixed or our
feature is built and it's sitting within
the codebase. So, in a traditional
software development life cycle,
maintenance can be a reactive phase.
You're out for lunch, you're on call, or
maybe it's 3:00 a.m. in the morning and
you get an alert to say that your server
has fallen over. A ticket is sitting in
a backlog and it gets completely ignored
because there's just too much in the
backlog. In the AISDLC,
a breach, a new ticket, a channel
message in Slack, or some kind of a
schedule invokes Claude without any kind
of a person involved to perform
maintenance. Claude asynchronously goes
ahead and diagnoses and acts on that in
And in this case, it's generating its
own intent.md file based on the logs
that it's discovered or whatever ticket
or message it's been sent. Now, how this
works in practicality is you might
decide that you have certain metrics
that you want to uphold to. So, maybe in
your testing, a page falls over or your
API rate limit rapidly increases. That
might trigger an agent to go and
diagnose, create an intent, to diagnose
a problem, and offer a set of
suggestions, but all before you've even
got to your computer. So, the whole
premise of this document is we're moving
past agents just being involved in the
build step to being employed in the
whole software development life cycle.
How can we start to reduce the amount of
human time involved in each one of these
steps, but importantly keeping humans in
the loop for the important review steps.
It depends on your workflow and your
need and your team, but you can have as
many humans involved in each step or
agents or purely just agents on their
own if there's low criticality. I've
worked in a lot of companies and I've
worked with a lot of companies with
their AI SDLC and the thing is there
really is no one size fits all. If
you're using something like superpowers
or B mad or you've developed your own
version of this, I wouldn't throw it
completely out the window to adopt what
Anthropic is doing here. There are so
many different ways to approach this
from loops to graph engineering, fully
automated loops, large orchestrated
systems
all the way to civilization engineering.
I'd love to hear how you're working your
software development life cycle even if
it's a simple as plan mode or complete
vibe code yolo. If you want to learn how
to make yourself or your development
team AI native in terms of software
development life cycle, highly recommend
you check out switch dimension. You can
sign up the waitlist there for the next
cohort. Thanks so much for your time
guys. I'll see you next week.